foreign
[Music]
definitely is getting more interesting
and the games have a lot more meat on
the bone where 1355 hopefully we get a
couple games with black so we can really
flesh out some accelerated dragon theory
let's roll the cameras hope you guys can
hear me fine let me know because I want
to I always want to make sure that when
I do YouTube videos the sound is okay so
if I'm peeking or something let me know
but it should be good singular 1400 and
we're facing the English C4 now my
recommendation against one D4 is gonna
be well I actually haven't decided yet
whether I'm recommending the king's
Indian or the grunfeld I'm leaning
toward recommending the grunfeld as my
official recommendation against one D4
openings
now again C4 if you want to be a
principal to Andy you have to learn E5
right so the way that I'm building this
opening repertoire for you in the speed
run I'm trying to teach you the most
principled lines the lines that are
going to annoy your opponent the most
and even if your rating is on the Lower
Side you want to avoid taking opening
shortcuts right and it's easy to take a
shortcut and say hey I'm a queen's gamma
decline player I'm gonna go E6 and D5
here absolutely nothing wrong with that
but if you want to play principal chess
the move that really takes it to White
is E5 and here there's a fork in the
road which we'll talk about after the
game I'll give you a little bit of
context on English opening theory of
course you can think of this as a
reversed closed Sicilian so Knight C3 is
the main move and here once again black
has a bunch of different viable setups
there's the move Bishop f8 to B4 which
if you've watched my Blitz Games you'll
notice that I play this move almost
exclusively but it leads to some
incredibly complex positional struggles
and I think a simpler line a more
approachable line for players of
intermediate level is just to develop
the Knight for now to F6 this does not
commit to any system of development in
particular well that's not totally true
it prevents us from pushing our Pawn to
F5 which constitutes a rather ambitious
but viable response to to the English so
we're precluding the possibility of F5
and here once again another fork in the
road for black
there's a bunch of different
possibilities here we're going to play
the move D5 uh in this game reaching a
reverse accelerated Dragon that's really
how you should think of this opening
it's an accelerated Dragon where white
is an extra Tempo and of course black is
playing White
there's of course the move Bishop B4
here as well which is similar to Bishop
before in the previous move you can just
continue developing with Knight C6 but
after the game I will show you a typical
scenario that often happens to players
who are not familiar with English Theory
the dangerous thing about this setup
from Black's perspective is that if you
just develop your pieces without a
second thought if you just put your
pieces on natural squares very often you
actually end up getting under serious
positional pressure and I'll give you a
couple examples of that after the game
so in this case we're gonna play the
most principled move which is D7 D5 and
I'm going to write down
some stuff to not forget it
show
examples of
misplaying
all right and obviously we take back
with the Knight
and Bishop G2 so our opponent continues
to follow the natural path
now here you might be tempted
extrapolating from uh the theory of the
accelerated Dragon to play the move
Bishop E6 but it's important to remember
that we are down to Tempo so Bishop E6
here is actually inaccurate I think for
several reasons but most importantly it
allows to to White to strike
with an early D2 D4 which leads to
tension in the center the black is not
entirely prepared for because black is
the one down a Tempo so the move here
it's not C6 either because again C6
allows D4
we want to play a clever move that
prevents D4 and increases our clamp on
the D4 Square in fact the battle is
going to revolve in the opening largely
around our ability to prevent first and
foremost the D2 D4 Pawn break and that
is why we drop our Knight back to B6 we
also don't take on C3 because that trade
in the Sicilian and by extension in the
reverse Sicilian plays right into
White's hands it increases wide's
control of the center and it helps white
white push D4 and it opens the B file
which you might notice there is a B7
Pawn that the bishop is already
pressuring Knight F3 we obviously
respond with Knight to C6 defending the
pawn and once again preventing D4
and then our dark squared Bishop in in
such positions a little context for
people watching on YouTube I I just
played a long Blitz session and I was
talking about how a lot of Chess GMS and
commentators they like to use the phrase
in such positions especially with the
Russian accent okay in such positions
and in such positions okay the plan is
typical yeah okay and I think it's an
overrated phrase because even the
players and people who use that phrase
don't exactly know what it means
um so in such positions the dark Squad
Bishop belongs on E7 now in this precise
position the dark squared Bishop belongs
on E7 and only on E7 what are the other
possibilities of development well we
could play Bishop D6 but once again I'm
a broken record but Bishop D6 walks
right into D4
now the move Bishop C5 is harder to
refute and it might make sense from a
logical standpoint right you're just
making it even harder for white to push
D4 but the bishop on C5 you might notice
is vulnerable to several different
things first and foremost there's this
idea of playing A3 B4 that you should be
familiar with if you're a sicilian
player there's also uh the annoying
night jump to E4 a white could also put
the queen on C2 and x-ray the bishop so
you should notice that the bishop on C5
just is a little bit unsafe and so we
want to develop a little bit more
modestly here with Bishop E7 all right
and then we want a castle and then we
want to bring the other Bishop out
usually to E6 as white often does In the
Sicilian of course you could also bring
it out to G4 but the bishop on G4 in
such positions doesn't really do
anything and when I say in such
positions here I mean positions with a
fee and kettled Bishop right we could
play Bishop G4 but it's a paper tiger
that pin is not dangerous at all white
plays E3 okay so here it's important to
talk about the idea of changed
circumstances right I just talked a lot
I talked up a storm about the importance
of preparing of preventing D4 so
extrapolating from that you might say
hey E3 threatens D4 well let's stop D4
at all costs and you might come up with
an idea like Queen to D3 or you might
say well let's go Bishop G4 let's try to
pin this Knight to make D4 as difficult
as possible but pawn moves change the
structure and so you have to reassess
the danger level of these ideas when the
structure changes and what you might
know notice is that after white plays D4
in this version
that's not nearly as dangerous as it was
just a couple moves ago because here we
trade on D4 white has to recapture with
the pawn eventually and what kind of
structure do we reach as a result well
that's called the iqp structure the
isolated Queen pun structure and a
shorthand way of evaluating who's better
in an iqp structure is to see who
controls the square in front of the
isolated Queen pawn and just to look to
see whether the side with the isolated
Pawn has attacking chances against the
opposing side's King which is often the
appeal of playing an iqp structure and
here in both cases this position favors
us
I'm in Queen D3 by the way not a bad
move at all not a bad move at all it's a
high level move but in this game we're
going to play it simple and we're
actually going to allow the move d4 and
what I'm going to attempt to show you is
that in the resulting position we
control the D5 Square
and we control the keys to the kingdom
our opponent confidently blitzes out
D4 we take on D4 and of course white get
can take back with a knight but we're
just going to trade Knights and
potentially we're even gonna trade
Queens I'm not totally sure we're going
to trade Queens there we'll see we'll
cross that bridge if we get there but um
our opponent takes back with a pawn I
actually think Knight takes D4 might
have been the only clear path to
equality for white and I'll show you
guys why afterward what is the key move
in this position it's harder to shoot at
a moving Target remember that and it's
important to pile up on the Square in
front of the iqp so what developing move
fits the bill here well if we play
Knight T5 immediately right it's less
important to occupy the square than it
is to control it and don't confuse
occupying a score with controlling these
are two separate things if you play
Knight T5 what you're allowing is Knight
takes D5 Queen takes D5 and then a
knight jump to E5 opening up a discovery
on the queen and things get really
unpleasant we kind of slip away from the
ledge the move is Bishop E6 Bishop to F6
is interesting you're attacking the pawn
but you're still allowing the pawn to
push forward to D5 now you might say hey
in that position you have Knight before
and I agree Bishop F6 is actually a
great move here but we're trying to play
sort of strict positional chess I'm
trying to play by the rules kind of lack
of creativity and that's by Design
so hopefully we'll get a chance to I'll
play our opponent in this position so we
have achieved what we set out to do I
would say that black is maybe only a
tiny smidge better uh maybe the position
is still even equal because the iqp in
this case is not a big weakness for
white white can defend it quite easily
with Bishop E3 so it's not like white is
losing the spawn imminently
um but it is somewhat of a liability of
course white has the major asset as they
do in the English which is this fiancado
bishop uh which sits on a very nice long
diagonal but our pieces are are also
very nicely positioned everything is
very compact everything is close to the
center and we've got many more ways to
improve our position you should already
just by looking at this for a couple of
moments identify a bunch of ways in
which you can a intensify the pressure
on the isolated Queen pun and B simply
improve your position and bring more
pieces into the game and there's kind of
a classic way to continue doing that
what am I talking about what's the sort
of very traditional follow-up in such
positions there is Bishop F6 once again
by the way
but I'm talking about Queen D7
and we just have to test that Queen d795
we can trade and white does get rid of
the iqp there so that is a drawback of
Queen D7 it's the move Knight to E5 in
response
and then after the trade white takes
back with a pawn and I'm not entirely
sure what to make of the resulting
structure so that might be something
that's worth dodging maybe we should
start with the move Bishop F6 and hit
the pawn first
and control the E5 Square so let's
calculate Bishop F6 I'm a little bit
concerned about this weird looking move
Knight C3 to E4 which seems to invite
black to take the pawn on D4 we capture
D4
but if you keep calculating after Knight
takes D4 Knight takes D4 the knight from
E4 jumps into C5 that's a lot of arrows
that's a long line but at the end of the
line the Knight on Z4 is loose the pawn
on B7 is hanging so that just doesn't
Inspire confidence but after Bishop F6
Knight E4 Bishop takes D4 Knight takes
D4 we can actually take on D4 with the
queen and the point of inducing a queen
trade is that in the resulting position
after Queen D4 Knight D4 Knight C5 and
this will be impressive if somebody can
get this what is Black's move in that
resulting position hopefully you were
able to follow along
what's Black's move in the position
after Knight C5 with the Queen's off the
board what does black have
it's Knight C2 there's a fork on C2 and
even if you didn't visualize the line
you should see that the Rooks are on
forkable square is a black snide from D4
jumps into C2
and so on the basis of this line and I
will say that at a Grand Master Level
the position is entirely unclear I mean
I I think our opponent has done a
phenomenal job in the opening thus far
but white has more at stake here if he
goes wrong okay if white makes a couple
passive moves he's going to slip into
passive mode Bishop E3 played and once
again we think about Queen D7 but yet
again Queen D7 runs into 95
unfortunately and after 95 to E5 we lose
the pawn on B7 at the end of the line so
I actually still don't want to go Queen
E7 I amend what I just said but what we
can do instead is increase our control
of the square in front of the iqp and
the more familiar you are with typical
plans in iqp structures the more fluent
you will be at finding these types of
ideas what we're going to do here is a
very typical move Knight C6 to B4 and
don't be fooled by the aggressive
appearance of this move this achieves
the same thing that 97 would achieve
it's just that 97 allows the extra
option of Knight F3 to G5 right we're
keeping a very close eye on this Knight
on F3 because by moving it white is
opening up the long diagonal which could
be unpleasant now you might say well
what about Knight E5 here well 95
doesn't make contact anymore with any of
Black's pieces so it's less dangerous we
can just leave that night sitting on E5
it's not really bothering us and the
knight from before can drop back to D5
establishing What's called the blockade
and once the blockade is established
well that's a step in the right
direction
um Queen C8 was a very good move
actually Quincy and Rook d8 would have
put the Rook on an X-ray with the White
Queen maybe was even the best move I'm
not claiming that I'm playing this in
the best way so we quickly dropped the
Knight back to D5
and I think a grand master approach for
white would be to play Knight C3 to E4
and aim the Knight for this very juicy
Square on C5 that's kind of annoying and
our opponent is firing on all cylinders
okay let's think
I kind of like the move Queen to C8 here
with black basically we are not so
worried about dropping our Bishop I mean
I don't love giving up the bishop and so
Bishop B7 comes to mind but Bishop E7
Knight C5 hits the bishop hits the B7
Pawn at the same time
and that's a little bit iffy
so let's actually calculate Bishop E7
Knight C5 now we can take the bishop on
E3 in that resulting position
then The Rook recaptures ah and then we
have a nice little reshuffling I think I
found something promising
I think I found something promising
but it's complicated
and I think white has a way to bail out
into equality there nonetheless
Bishop E7 Knight C5 Knight takes E3 Rook
takes E3
and then we just play Bishop E6 to D5
okay we can also do this immediately we
can replace the Knight with the bishop
Knight takes E3 and then Bishop D5 in
this position okay does that idea kind
of make sense what we're trying to do is
take the sting out of the move Knight E4
to C5 which with the bishop already on
D5 no longer carries the threat so I
actually think this might be the
simplest approach but we're gonna start
the see the problem with Knight takes C3
is that it allows F take C3 and white
essentially on iqps his Pawn this is a
positive Pawn structure transformation
for white we're going to play Bishop E7
I need to accelerate my Pace just a
little bit I'm running off of the mouth
here
um so we're gonna wait for Knight C5 and
then play Knight takes E3 and the idea
of switching the move order like that is
that in that position if white plays fe3
we can snap the Knight off the board and
ruin White's Pawn structure permanently
Bishop takes E5 DC and then the Knight
can jump into C4 and start harassing a
bunch of white spawns the position
remains extremely unclear there
but it seems to me that black has
perhaps a slightly easier game
so yeah this is definitely thus far
there was one guy we played in a
rosalimo if you remember a couple of
couple videos ago where our opponent
basically hung with me on equal terms
for most of the game
and thus far I have to give major props
to my opponent I mean this is not black
is not better here I think I
misevaluated this slightly I was a
little over optimistic based on the fact
that we have control of the square in
front of the iqp but my opponent is
convincing me otherwise what what white
is doing so expertly is using the iqp
and making the most of it right when
you've got a weak Pawn you have to
compensate for that with active piece
play and this is precisely what white is
doing white is playing very actively
doing everything he can to disrupt the
coordination of our pieces and this is
almost a blunder but it's not oh my gosh
Knight G5 so it looks like a blunder why
because Knight takes E3 snaps off the
defender of the G5 Knight but our
opponent sees Knight takes E6 in return
which leads to more complications Knight
takes d8 Knight takes D1 Knight takes d8
and if Knight takes B2 the Knight takes
on B7 and white is okay so one simple
option for black here is to play Knight
takes E3 Knight takes C6 take the queen
and then simply take the Knight on 28
and after Rook a takes D1 we play the
move like C6 and perhaps black is just a
tiny bit better but that's going to be a
tough end game to win that's going to be
a tough end game to win the alternative
in this position is of course to play
Bishop F5 what we do not want to allow
is Knight takes C6 and this is a tough
decision even for me so let me think
about this for a second
I like the look of Bishop F5 I feel like
Knight G5 is a paper tiger
I feel like this is a paper tiger and I
think we should keep the pieces on the
board
let's give it a shot I don't see a
follow-up for white I I think white has
succumbed slightly to one mubitis and
has granted us an important tempo
because now of course Knight takes E3 is
a massive threat actually very easy to
blunder right very easy to forget that
this is a move because our opponent
might fall into the illusion that oh the
Knight on D5 is our strongest piece so
we're not going to give it away very
common reason for blunders when you make
a positional assumption oh one piece is
stronger than another so the trade is
not going to happen right I think you
kind of see what I'm saying but you fail
to evaluate the position concretely and
to see that the trade is warranted for
tactical reasons
now white is experiencing some
logistical problems here because
apart from Knight takes E3 both of our
Bishops are making contact with both of
our opponents Knights which is not a
pleasant scenario for white
the best move here for white and it's
not an easy move for you know for for a
for a newer player to play not because
you know not trying to to condescend
this is just an objectively difficult
thing to do is just to kind of make a
Zen move like Bishop E3 back to C1 and I
think this is what white should actually
play and the point is to prevent Knight
take C3 and if we play H6 in that
position which we very well might then I
just drops back to F3 and there we go
right I I kind of called it our opponent
just collapses he's unable to deal with
everything that's going on and short
circuits and gives us a free piece we
have several ways to win the piece we
can play Knight takes C3 because the
Knight on G5 is literally now hanging
but while we're at it and white is going
to get a pawn for the piece right what
we don't want to do is play Bishop takes
G5 first that would be a huge mistake
because then if you look very carefully
well actually maybe we can get away with
that move but why does Knight takes D5
oh actually that's an interesting idea
no it doesn't work
Bishop takes G5 Knight takes D5 Knight
takes D5 Bishop takes G5 and our Queen
is overextended we're gonna end up
giving back the Knight on D5
so let's play it simple and let's do
what we originally intended and just
play Knight takes E3 and yes we are
allowing white to improve his structure
by the way the same would have been the
case after Knight takes C3 would have
done the other thing on the other side
leading to what's called a hanging Pawn
structure but what I like here is that
we have the bishop pair I love that we
have the bishop pair and we have an
extra Bishop and we have an extra dark
squared bishop and the reason that's
important is because the pawn on E3 has
now become a Target essentially the
target has shifted one file to the left
from the iqp to now the pawn on E3 which
can be easily targeted with a knight
from C4 with a rook from E8 and if we
can get white to play E4 another kind of
idea that a lot of players will stumble
on they think oh this is an intimidating
move no it's not because now once again
the target has shifted and again the
target has shifted to the D4 Pawn
White's Center may seem imposing but
it's actually a massive liability we
have an extra piece and we can easily
use our minor pieces to harass White
Center and provoke more weaknesses but
we got to be careful about how we do it
the careless Bishop G6 actually loses
the piece who can tell me why what
happens after Bishop G6 and don't worry
I will speed up just a little bit here
in the late middle game which means I
might not explain as thoroughly but
these couple next moves are still
important what happens after Bishop ship
back to G6 yeah H4 and we're gonna have
to sack our Bishop for two pawns because
if we move our Bishop back there white
can actually throw in E5 and then H5 and
we want to avoid that with a 10 foot
pull yeah we do so instead we should
move the bishop on this diagonal where
should we go well we can go back to E6
but then that allows D5 with Tempo so I
think we shouldn't hesitate to play what
may seem like an awkward move actually
the more I look at this I think Bishop
C8 was actually the best move just drop
the bishop back to its initial square
but leave open the Queen's contact with
the D4 pawn and later on we're going to
redeploy that Bishop as necessary Bishop
D7 is also good we're up a piece for
goodness sakes and this has the benefit
of being able to put the bishop on C6 in
the event that white pushes the e-pawn
which knowing you know player around
1400 I think he might be tempted by E5 I
also think he might be very tempted by
the one movitus move H4 which is no
longer dangerous and which will send our
Bishop back to E7 big whoop right our
pieces are temporarily a little a bit
passive
so what's going to be our our kind of
broad plan here it's hard to talk about
a plan because the position is very
volatile right it can change in a
variety of ways and that will in turn
change our approach where you can push
the Deep on or the E Pawn or why you can
play on the king side so it doesn't make
sense here to come up with a specific
plan for black but on a broad level the
way in which we can improve our position
is to make moves such as C6 Queen C7 and
bring the Rooks into the game I think
that's an important step which all plans
are going to share in common is that the
Rooks ultimately we're going to try to
put on d8 and on E8 to create the
backbone of the pressure that we're
ultimately going to put on White Center
Pawns we're also going to be very
attentive to the moment that white
pushes one of the center pawns the
moment he does so it creates weaknesses
Square weaknesses if white plays E5 we
can take out the fianchetto bishop with
Bishop C6 okay 92 is super passive and
it's not imposing at all and this gives
us a chance to really take the
initiative away from White's hands we
have a super high level positional move
here which we're gonna make and I'm
gonna explain the logic behind it now
first thing I see is that 92 has a
concrete drawback okay what is its
concrete Tropic well it allows to check
on E3 which I know some of you guys are
seeing but the check alone isn't that
effective Bishop B3 King H1 but you can
combine that check with an idea that
aims at shipping away at White Center
right you can ship away at White Center
and I call this carving out what you're
doing is you're provoking a pawn move in
order to create a a weakness on a collar
complex in this case obviously the color
complex we want to weaken are the dark
squares because we have an extra dark
squared Bishop so how do we induce a
weakness on the dark Square complex well
we what we need to provoke is the move
d4 D5 if we provoke that move what I
want you to notice is that all of these
dark squares in the center become really
big particularly the E5 Square which can
be used as an outpost for either the
Knight or the bishop so how do we
provoke white into playing D5 there's a
couple of ways to do it but there is one
super classic tactical move that we can
play and some of you are already seeing
it I did not mention Bishop E3 by
accident this plays an integral role in
the Tactical justification it's not
Bishop C6 because that doesn't actually
create any threats
it is the move C7 C5
and of course the Tactical part is that
if white plays DC we Fork the pawn with
our Bishop Bishop E3 we can recapture it
and you might say well why is that good
well that's good because it trades upon
and it opens up the center and when
you're up a piece that's exactly what
you want we have achieved what we want
here and we have two approaches we can
occupy the square with our Bishop we can
play Bishop F6 or we can play the the
sexy looking knight C4 and throw a
knight onto E5 which looks absolutely
fantastic and that's actually what we're
gonna do let's go Knight C4
and what we're keeping the bishop on G5
maybe bishop B3 will come in handy I
think Knight C4 is more flexible and
it's more aggressive
and it should be self-evident to all of
you why the Knight on E5 is such a
monster piece and outpost like that just
sits on the position it makes it
impossible for white to do anything it
takes the bishop on G2 entirely out of
commission and you know you're beginning
to see hopefully why it is that people
make such a big fuss out of weakening
squares and weakening complexes of
squares and a square complex is just a
set of dark squares in this case the
complex is in the center right E5 is
weak but also E3 is weak and D4 is weak
and B2 one could argue is weak as well
so it's the set of dark squares in the
center that white has weakened and so by
occupying it we hold the keys to the
kingdom we hold total dominance over the
board if you're again if you're newer
and you're watching this you know I
don't really understand how this Square
thing works you don't really need to
what you need to know right now is that
square control is important and you sort
of need to familiarize yourself with the
concept of a square complex okay so an
important moment has occurred let's
forget about this Pawn for a second I'm
not interested in that on what I'm
interested in is to prevent the move E4
E5 because that's how a square complex
weakness is eradicated right you push
upon onto the square and you sever our
control over that square so we can do a
couple things we can play the move 95
and literally put our Knight on E5
that's the simple idea but what I really
like is actually now to drop our Bishop
back to F6 okay again we're trying to
keep maximum flexibility we're keeping
the Knight on C4 for the time being
maybe we'll drop it back to E5 but also
we're attacking B2 and if white gives us
a chance I mean we might take it with
our Bishop and Jeffrey in the chat by
the way thank you for that we have
Jeffrey Zhang uh leading American
Grandmaster participating in the chat
live so I feel the need to to step up my
own game which which is awesome
um so big big shout out if you're
watching on YouTube make sure to follow
I'm gonna shamelessly Shield Jeffrey's
new uh twitch stream
twitch.tv shakes totally worth a follow
you see I'm I'm totally corrupt I just
promote my friends and that's it people
don't realize I'm not interested in
expressvpn
because friends get priority Knight to
D3 okay so what do we do now well first
we identify the threat the threat is
obviously E5 we have a gazillion ways
that we can meet with meet this threat
you guys are probably thinking let's go
95 but we're gonna do it in a slightly
more classy manner okay what we're gonna
do
well what we're gonna do is something
very obvious and you should see this
possibility there's a pawn that pawn is
hanging and this will take a little bit
of calculation what Pawn's hanging well
Knight takes B2 right Knight takes B2
let's calculate can white play E5 no
because white loses the queen
so after Knight takes B2 which we're
gonna play White has to recapture then
we recapture with the bishop can white
play E5 no because the Rook is hanging
but you might say but Rook B1 and we're
gonna lose the B7 Pawn well don't panic
first of all you can lose that pawn and
still be up a piece and still be winning
so after Knight B2 Bishop B2 Rook B1
you can very well Play Bishop B5 and
what we have done by taking on B2 has
created a past Pawn on C4 and don't you
know fall under the misconception that
past pawns cannot be promoted in the
middle game they very well can be and
they will be
and I'm tempted to go for this line just
to show you that but the clinical
approach if you really wanted to be
greedy is to drop the bishop back to D4
and after King H1 who can tell me a move
that simultaneously defends the B7 pawn
and prevents the move E5 we're not going
to do this we are going to go Bishop E5
here because it's the simpler approach
excellent dark tiger got it Queen C7
guys B6 does not stop E5 right you only
check one box the move was Queen C7
right it stopped C5 and a defense B7 but
much simpler is just to say I don't care
about this one I care about this Pawn
so let why take what is white actually
doing on B7 right this is an area of
improvement for a lot of players where
they look at a piece like they're
working to see well I need to get I need
to get rid of The Rook let's go Bishop
C8 let's go Queen C8 you don't need to
do either of these things because the
rook in and of itself is not actually
exerting any serious pressure we don't
need to go Rogue V8
we literally just want to push the pawn
here we go C4 and then once we go C3 the
pawn is forever anchored to the bishop
you should think of this as a checkpoint
right it's like a checkpoint in a video
game or a computer game where you hit a
spot and you basically you can die but
you'll go back to that spot so the pawn
on C3 is permanently anchored by the
bishop let's get it there and then let's
reassess the situation
the bishop is undefended yes okay Queen
H5 big deal right another one move
threat that we don't need to fear at all
all we need to do here is secure the
bishop right how do we secure the bishop
well we have a nice way to do it the
best way to defend a piece is with a
pawn so that should be your default
rookie eight defends it with a piece and
it weakens the F7 Pawn don't like it you
have six now you might look at this move
and say hey but first of all Ben
Feingold second of all are we not
worried about weakening the seventh rank
well no this is the simple answer
because white does not have the means
the Firepower to do anything about it
again this bishop on D7 it can't even be
attacked a second time if you look
carefully white can't put the second
Rook on the seventh ring why can play
the move Bishop G2 to H3 true
but then we just trade Bishops and we
can play Queen C8 in that resulting
position to force the queen trade as
well
even if white manages to create a mate
threat God forbid if white gets rid of
the bishop and then plays like Queen G4
that's a one move threat we can always
put a rook up to F7 if we're really
worried about the seventh rank
so I think what you should be focused on
as we're converting this Advantage is
just the power of concrete thinking and
the importance of not being reactive in
chess and saying oh this is scary
because of XYZ you always have to it's
okay to think like that you have to
think like that but you also have to
look at the position very concretely and
truly understand whether something is
scary so we take on H3
and now we identify the Rook as an
undefended piece the queen is always a
vulnerability combining those two
together we get the very classy move
Queen d8 to C8 forcing the queen trade
and you might say no it doesn't Force
the queen trade because white is Rook D7
and our opponent might play this move
Rook D7 loses the game on the spot and
I'll let you guys think of the reason
why
and perhaps we could say this move in
the chat even if white doesn't play Rook
D7 what do we do stress got it first
Rook F7 but not Rogue d8 Rook d8 is the
most popular wrong answer it's the right
idea but Rook takes the eight is check
it doesn't work Rook F7 avoids the check
and wins The Rook on D7 okay
so which Rook do we take with it doesn't
really matter
right you can play rokef C8 you can play
Rook ac8 but if you want to be super
classy and if you want to use tactics to
your benefit notice that we have the
possibility of a check on D4 and that
can be used in the event that white
takes A7 so Rook ac8 is the clinical
move and it also sets a trap our
opponent might mindlessly grab the pawn
on A7 and allow Bishop D4 with a fork
the reason the actual reason I'm taking
with the a rook and I'm being super
pedantic here deliberately
is because the other Rook can be used
for what purpose what can be used for
the purpose of smoking the white Rook
out of the seventh rank with Rook F7 and
you might say but didn't you say The
Rook on B7 isn't scary well the
circumstances have changed right now our
goal is to promote the C pawn and The
Rook on B7 has just become a nuisance
because the Queens are off the board so
our sequence of events is to smoke The
Rook away from B7 and then just
basically push the pawn supporting it if
necessary with both of our Rooks and
when the time is right we're going to
use our Bishop to knock White's Rock off
of whatever blockading post it's going
to occupy so Rook C1 has been played
we can start by pushing C3 we can
actually do it in this order let's do it
in this order there is zero rush to
playing Rook F7 white still cannot take
on A7 and he just did and that ends the
game okay Bishop D4 and this is how you
integrate traps into your play right you
talk about tricky players
to be a tricky player you don't need to
constantly BS and sacrifice move quality
if you're experienced you can seamlessly
weave traps with the way that you
normally play okay what do we do now
well there's one more nuisance to
eliminate so rather than C2 I like the
simple Rook f2d8 pick up the pawn then
go C2 and go Rook D1 and dislodge The
Rook from C1 make white give it away for
the pawn and the rest will be easy
foreign
and you might be like okay the entire
all of these explanations in like the
last two minutes might have been
unnecessary but my like coaching
philosophy my philosophy of helping
people improve is to emphasize that when
you promote the right kinds of habits in
totally winning positions you should
think of these positions as a training
ground for building the right habits
right this is a low stakes situation
because you know you're going to win the
game basically whatever you do although
never underestimate people's power uh to
mess things up so you know it's it's
like you still have to try to push
yourself to be precise and before you
know it
um you will start being precise in more
complicated positions
I'll let you research the quote yourself
and figure out who he was talking about
okay Rook takes C8
and here comes Johnny Rook C2 and queen
H5
and it's mate no stalemate plenty of
bond moves
the game is over
I miss Maiden two apparently shame on me
okay now the simplest is to drive the
king back to G2 Paving the way for a
check on C2 so the retreating move Queen
H5 check perhaps there's a faster mate I
don't care I see a mate we're going for
a maid and the ladder made Queen D1
is coming to a theater near you and that
ends the game and that was one of our
longest games thus far right around 40
moves 39 moves
and it was a nice game it was it was a
rich positional game and I have to give
kudos to our opponent who played
extremely well really until the peace
blunder
and and even you know induced I think a
couple of inaccuracies so so let's delve
into the analysis
and this will be sort of a little
opening overview
on top of a game analysis
all right let me pull up chess base
so C4 E5 so there's there's many schools
of thought for for how to face the
English and it really depends on which
opening you play against D4 right so the
first step is to ask yourself what you
play against D4 if you're a queen's
gamma decline player C4 is the least
dangerous move against qgd players
because you can basically just play A6
and white in many cases just ends up
going D4 and transposing there are a
couple of ways that white could keep a
unique English flavor so there is stuff
you still need to learn in particular
the most common is to play this ready
setup with Knight F3 and G3
white good play the move E4
but here after D5 you transpose into a
variation of the exchange French that
you have to learn if you want to play
this with black but realistically it's
not dangerous I think this is the best
move
and uh black is doing completely fine
now things get a little bit more
complicated if for example you are a
let's say you're a grunefeld player okay
and if you're a grundfo player just to
show everybody what the grinfeld is the
grunfeld is when you play G6 now the
king's Indian is Bishop G7 allowing E4
and in the grunfeld you strike with the
immediate D5
I might say well look what's the big
problem let's just do that Knight F6
Knight C3 G6 White's gonna play D4 no
White's not gonna play D4 White's gonna
play E4 and Gruen fall players often get
move order like this and you've gotten
move out into a king's Indian right you
basically have to go D6 and after D4 you
have a king's Indian
which by extension if you're a king's
Indian player the English is also not a
big problem for you because you can just
go G6 or you can go Knight F6 and G6 and
we're basically happy now white can keep
the English flavor against the king's
Indian it's actually quite an annoying
opening that's where white does not
Advance the pawn to D4 white keeps the
pawn on D3
and that's partially why I like to play
E5 against C4 even though I'm making
lifelong King's Indian player so I've
halfway the king's Indian setup against
the English but I really feel that e45
is the principled line
um if you're a slav player you're also
experiencing some problems against C4
the slav is D5 C4 and C6 does anybody
know why the move C6 here like what is
the Annoying line that slav players have
to learn on top of of course regular
slop stuff and we're getting a little
technical here but nonetheless
what does white do here to try to move
order black into a line they don't know
yeah E4
and after E4 D5
it transposes after D4 into a pan-off
Karo Khan
into a pan of Karo Khan it's it reaches
the same exact move order as after
ce4c604 D5 takes takes in C4 you get the
same exact position so if you're a slav
player and you want to play C6 you also
have to learn the pan of which is not a
big problem to learn and black is doing
totally fine but you just have to keep
these things in mind and I think the
easiest way to avoid all of that is just
to learn E5 to invest some time and
learn this move and it exposes you to a
whole set of positions okay
penob is not a problem black is equal in
the piano but you have to know Theory it
can be very dangerous if you don't know
Theory so what we're not going to do is
delve deeply into all of White's English
setups I'm just going to introduce them
to you apart from G3 which our opponent
played there is the Four Knights English
Knight F3 and here if we face this we're
going to play a super cool line that I'm
going to introduce to you that starts
with E4 this is a very modern line it's
a it's a pawn sacrifice and it's really
only recently arrived on the scene but
traditionally black plays Knight C6 and
here the classical four nights English
is E3 you might have seen me with white
play E4 a lot this is a recent move
that's really arrived on the scene and
the idea as I talked about in the
previous stream actually is Bishop C5
the center fork trick 95 95 and D4
and let's see who paid attention to the
previous speed run if black plays Bishop
D6 he's already losing
why is black already losing here
because of the move C4 C5 and Black's
minor Pieces Just collapse just cave in
so
so there's all this stuff but G3 is
still considered the most popular and we
play D5 reaching essentially a reverse
Sicilian this is an incredibly well
studied opening there is a lot of theory
here but it's quite easy to understand
the main setup for Black
which is why I'm choosing this is my
official recommendation
so after Bishop B7 I'm going to plug
this into chess base
so that I don't give you any inaccurate
information
but to my knowledge the move E3 here is
not particularly effective let me check
how many times it's been played it's
been played a handful of times and even
by some strong players
but it's not dangerous it's not it's not
a topical line the main line continues
D3
black of course Castle's King side
and here already there is a bit of a
fork in the road there's A3 preparing B4
and there's Bishop C1 to E3 this is the
typical Square Four whites dark squared
Bishop just by process of elimination
Now by popularity the main line is A3
and here I'm just gonna introduce this
line by showing you the next couple
moves you play Bishop E6 so you actually
don't play A5 you allow white to play B4
and here you carry out a very cool trick
we play the move A5
now what the heck is black doing black
shows blundering upon B5 Knight D4
and Knight takes E5 looks like we've
just blundered away a Central Pawn
what's funny is that David Howell the
Grand Master he played this against me
and he beat me with with white in this
line but this is an exchange sacrifice
that most people will stubble into
unwittingly Black's move here is Bishop
to F6 and suddenly white experiences
major problems uh with his Knights
because if Knight F3 then you take and
you take on C3 and you win a piece
the Knight is nowhere else to go
um so white has to support it with F4
if white plays Bishop F4 black is a very
pretty move
and a a very important idea to know
anytime you have this construction
especially if there's a Pawn on G3 what
move do you have to remember
black to play and win if you're watching
on YouTube pause and figure this out
it's worth your while G5 chases the
bishop away and wins a piece very good
so white has to play them of f4
now uh black plays Bishop E5 fe5 and
Knight to B3 this is the Crux
of Black's idea because if the Rook
moves then you have Queen to D4 check
forking the knight in the king so
actually what black has to do and what
David Howell uh did is is just Bishop C1
to E3 you have to cover the D4 square
and Sack The Exchange but according to
Modern engines and I analyze this black
has the move Knight b60 D5 you're trying
to force trades because you're up in
exchange and only black can be better
here there are some correspondence games
here
um there are some OTB games one of them
continued uh Bishop C5 rookie eight
and a guy named Jensen 2470 I am played
94 but it turns out after a simple move
like Queen D7 black is incredibly solid
in the center
um another OTB game continued A4
and now very strong would have been just
to solidify your queen side structure
with B6
Bishop D4 and now to throw in another
prophylactic H6 to prevent the knight
from jumping into D5 and then you go
Rook d8 or you can go Rook AC 8 and
eventually Bishop H3 black essentially
is the only only side having fun here
so we went quite deep but it's important
to know the Slime because if white
doesn't know what to do after Knight T4
he's very likely to take on E5 now
instead
in this position the main line is Knight
back to D2
covering the B3 Square white can also
play Rook B1 this is second in
popularity and this leads to some very
interesting positions so for example
after Knight T2 uh black kind of eats
into White's structure with C6 this is
the theoretical move BC Knight C6 and
already I would argue that you can play
this move OTB with black like you can
know only this and you're already gonna
be fine
the main line continues Rook B1 and now
black cements the weakness on A3 by
pushing the pawn up to A4 another very
typical move in such structures and then
you go Rook C8 and quickly you can
reposition your knight back to D4 and
even make your way to B3 it's an easy
position to play and I really think that
unless white is super familiar with
typical plans and structures it's easy
for white to fall into passive mode and
get a worse position the engine just
gives basically zeros everywhere here
last thing I'll say in this position is
that if white plays Rook B1 then you
actually need to defend the E5 Fawn now
it is a threat and you can do so by
pushing F6 remember that if you have a
bishop on this diagonal F6 is not nearly
as weakening as it would otherwise be
and now again the main move is Knight D2
played by Carlson and others if white
plays Knight takes D4 then of course you
recapture with the pawn to clamp down on
White's Queen side Knight to A4 Bishop
to D5 trading off the fianchetto bishop
and black is doing totally fine so this
is a very short elevator pitch kind of
overview overview of the main lines here
there are Sidelines white can play the
immediate A3 B3 is quite popular as well
but uh for the time being let's switch
back to what our opponent played E3
okay any questions about that
let's see what people are saying I'm
reading the chat
Jeffrey says there's a super GM subtlety
after E3 you'll have to explain so we
Castle
we allow the move d4 and we take it
and we reach this position now of course
as I pointed out during the game
um there is the possibility of playing
Knight takes D4 and by the way I hate to
jump around too much but I did promise
that I'll show you why the English can
be dangerous if black plays kind of
nonchalant developing moves so let's
rewind a little bit and talk about that
for a second this is important so let's
say the black plays the 90s Knight C6
and then Bishop E7 already black is
worse and the way to understand this
position is to understand that black no
longer is able to push D5 and if you're
not able to push D5 that basically means
you have to position your Pawn on D6 and
it's just passive it's passive white can
play this common setup with E3 and 92
this was introduced to me as the bobbin
extended we played this with black In
the Sicilian just a couple games ago and
black has no obvious plan
cramped passive white has this typical
plan of pushing the beep on forward and
orchestrating some Queen side pressure
and yeah you can play this bishop E6
castles you can even try to push through
D5 but if you play it down a bunch of
Tempe you're not gonna enjoy yourself
and white can even Counter Strike with
D4 and this gets super super nasty
because you can't take on C4
uh so okay you can play Queen D7 here
but uh after something like Knight to D5
it's it's unpleasant
it's unpleasant
um
and and you should remember that right
that's why you need a concrete setup
against the English there are setups
where you actually put your Bishop on C5
um and Jeffrey I'll get to your point in
a second there are setups where you play
Bishop C5 but again after E3 you're just
biting on granite and in some lines
black tucks the bishop away on A7 for
like a rainy day I looked at these
setups I think black is worse here uh
partially because you're actually
allowing the pawn to get to D4 in one
Fell Swoop so these are interesting
setups but I don't particularly like
them I don't think they're very sound
and and I think the way you should play
is is D5 I'm pretty insistent on that so
we will I'm sure face this again and we
will talk more about Theory and Jeffrey
is making a very interesting point so
after D4 ed4 apparently the move Knight
takes D4 was very strong very
interesting point why is the move Knight
D4
so strong well let's figure it out well
my plan was to play Knight 64. I suppose
white plays e takes D4 and the Crux of
the matter is that after we play C6 to
Halt the progress of the d-pawn can
anybody tell me what very scary move
white now has at his disposal and this
is the entire reason that you move the
Knight on it from F3 in the first place
and this should be obvious right because
at this point you should have a pretty
good grasp of what each side wants
yeah phenomaster has it right black
white plays D5
they might say well why is D5 so
dangerous well first of all white is
eradicating his weakness the iqp but
what often happens is that once the iqp
is eliminated the Dam breaks and the
side of the more active pieces is going
to benefit now which side is the more
active pieces well it's clearly white
and it's because of the placement of
this light squared Bishop black slide
scored Bishop is still on its developing
Square
so if you forecast a bunch of Trades
here after Knight takes D5 I actually
think white can even take back with a
queen
um maybe white can take with the bishop
but that end game is quite unpleasant
for black the engine does give equality
here with with a precise play
black needs to quickly put the other
Bishop on F6 to do the same thing to
white the white is doing to black but
nonetheless you can see that it's a
little bit it's a little bit iffy and
maybe maybe white should play Bishop
takes D5 maybe this is the way to fight
for an advantage and after Bishop F6
maybe the queen can come out to have
three The Rook to D1 and white is a bit
of an initiative that should sort of
make sense to you intuitively so D5 is
actually Unstoppable here and you can't
bring your Bishop out because you drop
B7 right so these subtleties are
important to appreciation and that is
why according to Jeffrey Bishop E6 here
was actually more precise than castling
because now if white plays D4 who can
explain to me what the difference is in
this position
and now you should have the aha moment
everything should kind of Click what
does black do here
not Knight D5 Knight T5 is premature you
don't need to occupy the square you
don't need to occupy the square to
control it controlling it is more
important
C6 exactly you play C6 now and D5 is no
longer possible because the bishop is an
added defender of that square
not Queen C8 guys Queen C8 allows
exactly what white wants it allows the
pawn to move forward
you need to control that square now why
is Knight D5 bad here well Knight C5 is
bad because you're biting off more than
you can chew and you can basically get
Stein as part 11 after takes in rookie
one I'm referencing a famous game where
black encountered similar problems on
the e-file and was never able to Castle
um and and thank you Jeffrey for this
point this is a very instructive point
and you're getting introduced right now
to basically GM level opening Theory and
like how things work but what you should
take away from this is that everything
can be understood right it's not like oh
Bishop E6 is better because it is it's
better for a specific reason that you
can carve out with enough analysis and
persistence
so in any case we're getting deep here
let's get into the middle game we play
Bishop E6 white doesn't play Knight
takes C4 and we breathe a sigh of relief
okay so Bishop F6 I think is a
reasonable move to attack D4 there were
other ways we could play we could put
the Knight on D5 we could play the
immediate night before a night before to
D5 I'm sure if you look with an engine
Bishop F6 is probably not the best move
to Echo the line I was talking about 94
is what I was really worried about
what's up chess kid 94 is what I was
worried about and here we were
calculating Bishop D4 Knight D4 and we
concluded that Knight D4 is very
imprecise on account of this nasty
little move Knight to C5
attacking B7 and E6 and everything is
kind of hanging in the air but Queen D4
breathes new life into this line
because if white takes and plays Knight
C5 now there's this Fork this is the
line I was referencing during the game
now you should see it
but in this position it's really not the
end of the story and white can play a
move like Queen no not Queen G4 but
Queen H5 and I believe that white has a
very powerful initiative in response in
exchange for the pawn I mean there's an
ig5 ideas according to the engine black
is totally fine after the crazy F6 to
stop Knight G5 but this is scary I mean
the queen is vulnerable whites pieces
look very active it leads to
complications it leads to a super
complicated game if you're interested
you can surf around with an engine but I
don't want to get too bugged down in the
complications because Bishop E3 is what
really anybody under 2200 would play
automatically
and Knight to B4 preparing to increase
our control over D5 A3 by our opponent
which I think is inaccurate because it
sends the Knight where it wants to go
anyway
I think the correct move would have
indeed been to play Knight E4 once again
we would have dropped our Bishop back to
E7
and perhaps white can play Knight C5 we
go Bishop D5
maybe now it's time to chase the night
out of B4 since it can't get to D5 we
would have dropped back ah Knight C6
Runners the pawn aha
so this would have been a nasty little
way to play would have forced us to play
Knight A6
and of course now
we have been forced to ruin our Queen
side construct is it the end of the
world no because we still have this big
blockading piece on D5 but white can
play Knight E5 and keep piling it on and
despite the fact that white trades is
finchero Bishop with the queen coming to
F3 and the Knight to C6 you can sense
that white White's pieces are a lot more
active here so these types of positions
you want to try to avoid I think after
94 white maintains a small advantage
okay so but that's that's very very deep
stuff and A3 is intuitive white plays it
now but now after Knight C5 this has
lost a lot of its Effectiveness because
we can take on E3 and then we can take
on C5 and this is what I was discussing
during the game after Knight C4 with or
without Queen takes D1 I think black is
doing fine White's pawns are quite
damaged
and it's not so easy to keep everything
under wraps here if you're white
um so in any case I think things really
started going well things went wrong in
the span of just a single move I still
think here that if black white plays the
careful Bishop C1 why is not worse and
the engine gives zeros which I think is
pretty reasonable I mean black has we've
gained a bunch of Tempe right with white
dearly dallying around on the king side
but even if white just says sorry as my
old coach would say just I'm gonna go
back sorry white is still very solid
right white is still fundamentally sound
here as is black and the game takes on a
very positional character here the
engine recommends a simple love to move
like H6 even Knight D5 back to F6 is
interesting to make space for the other
night and try to trade off some pieces
when you're playing against an iqp you'd
normally want to trade minor pieces
because the fewer pieces are left the
the harder it is to apportion resources
because something has to defend the iqp
so if you don't have a lot of pieces
left you might end up just forcing all
of your remaining pieces to defend the
isolated Queen Pawn there's a great car
buff coach no game on this topic that
I've shown before on stream won't do it
now Knight C5 is the engine line and
there is a train on C5 the structure
changes and you get a very unclear end
game with both sides kind of having
their share of activity
and Jeffrey makes an important point
which is that it is psychologically very
difficult for really any player but
especially newer players to play these
types of retreating moves and admit that
you messed up and this is a big takeaway
from this game if you're considering
learning from White's perspective it's
like when you have sensed that you just
messed up right let's say you fell into
a one move itis kind of trap you made a
move that you thought was cool and then
you immediately realized that you've
just Twisted yourself into a knot your
first instinct should be to it should be
self-reservation you should make sure to
identify the threats and then just make
sure you're not losing any pieces and do
whatever it takes right because I think
White's problem is that he just sort of
panicked he's like oh this didn't work
out the way I wanted it to and then you
short circuit but rather than short
circuiting you say well what
specifically is Black's threat well if
you ask yourself that question you
should notice that it's 93 and Bishop G5
well how do we prevent it well you can
do it from two different ends you can
move the Knight away you can move the
Bishop Way the Knight is no good squares
because Knight F3 just happens to
blunder the night I suppose Knight H3 is
a way to defend your minor pieces but it
goes without saying that this is
ridiculously awkward and black is better
and so that really only leaves the
option of moving the bishop away why not
Bishop D2 because it cuts contact uh
between the queen and the pawn but it's
also possible and it right invites a
move like Knight C4 and Bishop C1 is the
best move both according to the engine
and according to what we what we
discussed
um apparently according to Leela Bishop
D2 is good and even the move Queen to F3
is not so bad attacking the bishop and
the idea is to meet Knight takes C3 with
oh actually I have to take C3 Aha and
you're counter attacking the bishop on
F5
this may seem to win a piece but
remember the very night that's being
attacked can also do the capturing
not to be forgotten about it it's a
complicated position
so in this game analysis we're doing
kind of a lot of open-ended analysis and
digging around and this might strike you
as boring and aimless but hopefully this
is helping you formulate a better
understanding of these complex positions
you never know when these ideas can come
in handy so you know this was an
open-ended game it's hard to make any
hard and fast conclusions but I still
think just analyzing deeply like this it
helps you acquire ideas and and Achieve
fluency and complicated situations now
once the piece was blundered I'm not
going to talk too much about the rest of
the game I'm just going to make a couple
of clarifications Bishop G6 here allows
H4
and funnily enough after Bishop F6 black
is actually getting away with it
black is getting away with it because
after H5 we can play Queen takes D4 and
once the queen is knocked out the bishop
can then capture H5 but that's luck and
after E5 Bishop E7 the bishop now has a
retreat his skin out of a trading score
but an escape Square on F5
all right and so Bishop G6 did work but
we did we played a more conservative
move a safer move
and I also think the top move and yeah
Knight E2 is kind of you know giving
giving the game away well the game has
already been given away if I was playing
white I would have probably tried to
muddy the waters but this is still
completely lost I mean this is just a
free piece actually Bishop C6 might be
inaccurate due to D5 which I missed so
perhaps here we should instead play Pawn
to C6 and really establish our control
over this light square and then bring
the bishop back to E6 and the Knight to
D5
yeah my apologies
um Bishop C6 was indeed imprecise
92 we found this nice tactical move C5
carving out the weak dark Square
and this is just a a sort of stock idea
that you should be aware of a very Con
on a very conceptual level
it occurs very commonly in every opening
it's a universal idea but if I had to
give you a a simple example of an
opening where an idea like this occurs
super frequently
it is the Karo Khan so take a look at a
very simple illustration of this concept
by none other than elephant himself and
here you will see why players in the
1800s often struggled
because they they were often unfamiliar
with sort of a basic positional
Concepts stuff that we now kind of take
for granted
so take a quick Gander at this game
this is a simple illustration of this
concept in wearing different clothes
essentially Marco against the lap and
two leading players of the 1800s
um
so in this position it's an isolated
sorry it's an obstacle Bishop end game
and white plays the move C3 C4
how do you think alapan responds let's
see who's paying attention to
the the general concept
now you identify the square you want to
carve out very good B6 B5 excellent and
Marco goes right into Black Sands he
plays C5 and he yields this incredible
Square on D5 right this is just now why
does an equivalent score on D6 but the
thing is white put the Knight there the
Knight on D6 is just looks good it
doesn't actually do anything that md5
Lords over the entire position and black
ends up winning the game by using the
Knight directly to break through on the
queen side to create a pass pawn and
then he accumulates his pieces there and
he ends up winning the game and
eventually the Knight is replaced by a
bishop so the D5 square is is an
integral part of the way in which alapan
wins this game nowadays people would
kind of automatically if we rewind lean
toward B3
and and not yield the square now black
can take and go B5 with the other pawn
and here I would go rookie C1 and if you
think about it in this case the effect
of the D5 score is still intense but
it's diminished because black has to
reckon with the weakness of the C6 pawn
and you know it's diluted essentially
uh but I can show you a zillion examples
of this I call this carving out you're
carving out a square
and we did something very similar here
with the move C5 just wearing different
clothes once again
um if D5 which happened in the game we
get this monster E5 square if DC then we
come around we pick up the pawn and with
the open D file we're gonna move our
Bishop away and White's gonna collapse
very quickly so D5 Knight C4
Bishop back to F6 controlling E5 winning
the pawn on B2 and dropping the bishop
back to E5 keeping our eyes on the prize
not fearing Rook B7 pushing the pawn now
the plan is very simple you're gonna
push it all the way
Queen H5 F6 a simple defensive move
protecting the bishop with a pawn and
now a little operation to force the
queen trade Bishop H3 and queen C8 and
again if Rook D7 here trying to
intercept it Rook to F7 ends the game
because the queen is undefended there's
no check on d8 there's no Queen E6
because of just Queen takes D7 and here
this loses the queen and so it loses the
game
takes takes C3 and of course white
hasten's defeat but if White had gone
Rook C2 we would have followed through
with our plan Rook F7 and then there's a
million ways to win but I like the move
even Rook to C4 just go after the E4
Pawn win both of white spawns and the
bishop is more than capable of Defending
C3 all by its lone Summits also
protecting the B8 Square so white
doesn't even have this check and the
moment white moves The Rook away you
push the pawn classic kind of concept
okay
so this ends the game and the rest is
clear without commentary
sure
that was a rich game that was a good
game I hope you enjoyed the analysis a
lot to take away from this there's a lot
of takeaways in the opening
and and a lot of takeaways positionally
I which I won't reiterate because there
were a lot of specific things but you
know I hope you've come away with a
feeling that you're more comfortable
with these types of positions especially
iqp structures thanks Jeffrey for all
the Insight this was super fun and uh
you know thanks again to the people
watching on YouTube for supporting the
channel and and making this possible
with your subscriptions
thank you all
[Music]